Guide to the C. Vann Woodward Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
C. Vann Woodward papers
1804-2004
1804-2000
MS 1436
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
40.26
97 boxes
2493.54
The papers consist of correspondence, writings, topical files, and an interview, primarily documenting the professional career of historian C. Vann Woodward.
Woodward, C. Vann (Comer Vann), 1908-1999
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of C. Vann Woodward, 1993 and 1995; gift of Susan L. Woodward, 2000; gift of Charles Joyner, 2005.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Arrangement
Arranged in six series and two additions: I. Correspondence, 1926-2000. II. Writings, 1935-1998. III. Subject files, 1947-1997. IV. Research files, 1873-1960. V. Yale, 1944-1997. VI. Personal, 1804-2000.
Scope and Contents
The C. Vann Woodward papers are a rich resource for studying the professonal life of one of the leading twentieth century American historians and the evolution of the teaching and writing of the history of the South during his lifetime. The arrangement of the papers into six series corresponds to groups of materials as they were found in Woodward's home. The heart (and majority) of the collection consists of correspondence and writings. From the correspondence the reseacher gains an understanding of the thought process that went into Woodward's approach to studying, writing, and teaching history. It also documents the collegial world of criticism that Woodward so highly valued. Woodward's friends, colleagues, and acquaintances included the leading lights in the history profession. Through letters that combined "candor with civility" they critiqued and commented on his research and writings, and he did the same for them. His relationships with his graduate students, as mentor directing pioneering research into new aspects of Southern history, professional colleague, and friend, is well documented in his letters to and from them. Of particular value in the Writing series are a number of unpublished short writings on a range of topics.
There is only scattered documentation of Woodward's involvement in the civil rights movement and its location is noted in the various series descriptions. There are photographs of him in the Writings series (Books - Mary Chesnut's Civil War - Photographs) and in the Personal series (Photographs, and Portrait unveiling).
Biographical / Historical
Once hailed as the "dean of American History," C. Vann Woodward left an indelible mark on the study of history through a career that spanned seven decades. With considerable literary skill and a keen understanding of the region and its myths, Woodward fashioned revisionist interpretations of economic, political, and racial divides in the post-Reconstruction, or "New," South that helped to introduce the study of southern history to scholars and students outside both the region and the field. He shattered heroic images of "Bourbon" Democrats and the booster ideal of a truly prosperous and "redeemed" New South, argued that the phenomenon of segregation was relatively recent and therefore reversible, and on the whole turned a more critical and analytical eye toward a field of study that had long been marred by sentimental and apologist scholarship. Woodward's writing laid a new foundation for the study of the South, and his seminal works are basic texts for students of southern history.
Comer Vann Woodward was born on November 13, 1908, in Vanndale, Arkansas, to Hugh Alison Woodward, a school administrator, and Bessie Vann Woodward, whose ancestors founded Vanndale. After attending grade school and two years of college in his home state, Woodward moved to Atlanta, Georgia, to attend Emory University, where his uncle, Comer Woodward, was dean of students. He graduated with a degree in philosophy in 1930. In between teaching jobs at the Georgia Institute of Technology, Woodward enrolled in graduate school at Columbia University. While in New York he met W. E. B. Du Bois, Langston Hughes, and other figures of the Harlem Renaissance. After receiving an M.A. in political science in 1932, Woodward returned to Georgia Tech and became involved in a campaign to raise funds for the defense of Angelo Herndon, an African-American communist and civil rights advocate who was being tried on a death penalty charge of inciting insurrection. He also became friends with Will Alexander, head of the Commission on Interracial Cooperation, and J. Saunders Redding, a prominent African American writer who taught at Atlanta University. In 1933, Woodward lost his job, a misfortune he blamed on budget cutbacks, though the administration had admonished him for his involvement in the Herndon case. After a brief turn as a surveyor of rural poverty in Georgia for the Works Progress Administration, he decided to enter graduate school at the University of North Carolina in Chapel Hill. While there he hoped to complete a biography he had begun writing about Populist leader Tom Watson.
While a student in Chapel Hill, Woodward met Glenn Boyd MacLeod, whom he married in December 1937, just after receiving his Ph.D. The following year he published his dissertation. The success of Tom Watson: Agrarian Rebel led to an invitation from Charles Ramsdell, editor of the History of the South series, for Woodward to write the volume on the New South. While doing research for the book, Woodward held a string of teaching jobs at the University of Florida (1937-1939), the University of Virginia (1939-1940), and Scripps College (1940-1943). On February 17, 1943, his only child, Peter Vincent, was born. Later that year, Woodward left Scripps for a three-year stint in the U.S. Naval Reserve, where he wrote classified accounts of naval battles for the Office of Naval Intelligence. One of his unclassified accounts, The Battle for Leyte Gulf, was published in 1947. That same year he accepted a teaching position at Johns Hopkins University in Baltimore. While still working on his book for the southern history series, Woodward published Reunion and Reaction: the Compromise of 1877 and the End of Reconstruction, based on his research for the early chapters of the New South book.
Woodward's long-awaited volume on the New South was finally published in 1951. Origins of the New South, 1877-1913 won the prestigious Bancroft Prize and cemented Woodward's reputation as one of the foremost authorities on the American South. From 1951 to 1952 he served as president of the Southern Historical Association. In 1954 he delivered the James W. Richards lectures at the University of Virginia, and in 1954-1955 he served as the Harmsworth Professor of American History at Oxford University.
Woodward's efforts on behalf of the civil rights movement in the 1950s also garnered much attention. In 1953 the N.A.A.C.P. invited Woodward and John Hope Franklin to assist in preparing a brief for the celebrated Brown vs Board of Education Supreme Court case. Two years later his Richards lectures, which boldly challenged prevailing histories of segregation in the South, were published as a best-selling book called The Strange Career of Jim Crow. The book was so influential that Martin Luther King, Jr. later called it "the historical Bible of the civil rights movement."
The 1960s and 1970s were perhaps Woodward's most productive years as a scholar. In the late 1950s he began co-editing the Oxford History of the United States series with Richard Hofstadter. In 1960, he published The Burden of Southern History and edited George Fitzhugh's Cannibals All!, and the following year he joined the Yale faculty as Sterling professor of history. In 1968 he edited a collection of essays by some of the most noted scholars of American History, published as The Comparative Approach to American History. He also served overlapping terms as president of both the Organization of American Historians and the American Historical Association in 1968-1969. His only son, Peter Vincent, died in 1969, at age 26, a few months before Woodward delivered his presidential address to the American Historical Association. In 1974, after a speech at Yale by controversial genetecist William B. Schockley was disrupted, Woodward headed a panel to outline the university's policy on freedom of speech. The Woodward Report, as it became known, still defines Yale's position on the right to free speech on campus.
Woodward retired from teaching at Yale in 1977, but he remained an active and productive historian. In addition to publishing numerous articles and book reviews, he edited Mary Chesnut's Civil War, which won a Pulitzer Prize in 1982. That same year, his wife, Glenn, died. In 1986 Woodward published Thinking Back: the Perils of Writing History, a retrospective look at his career and his critics. He was active in public life right up until his death. In October 1998, he co-sponsored a statement signed by 400 historians that denounced the impeachment of President Clinton. A month later, at the annual meeting of the Southern Historical Association, generations of southern historians marked Woodward's ninetieth birthday with a celebration of his life and work. He died on December 17, 1999, at the age of 91, in Hamden, Connecticut.
Historians -- United States; History -- Research; Southern States -- Historiography; Southern States -- History; Historians; Beale, Howard K. (Howard Kennedy), 1899-1959; Bickel, Alexander M.; Blassingame, John W., 1940-2000; Blum, John Morton, 1921-2011; Brewster, Kingman, Jr., 1919-1988; Brooks, Cleanth, 1906-1994; Du Bois, W. E. B. (William Edward Burghardt), 1868-1963; Durr, Virginia Foster, 1903-1999; Ellison, Ralph, 1914-1994; Evers, Medgar Wiley, 1925-1963; Fields, Barbara Jeanne; Franklin, John Hope, 1915-2009; Genovese, Eugene D., 1930-2012; Giamatti, A. Bartlett, 1938-1989; Hackney, Sheldon, 1933-2013; Hiss, Alger, 1904-1996; Hofstadter, Richard, 1916-1970; King, Martin Luther, Jr., 1929-1968; Lamar, Howard Roberts, 1923-; Lumpkin, Katharine Du Pre, 1897-1988; Malone, Dumas, 1892-1986; McFeely, William S.; McPherson, James M., 1936-; Moynihan, Daniel P. (Daniel Patrick), 1927-2003; Percy, Walker, 1916-1990; Potter, David Morris; Rose, Willie Lee, 1927-2018; Schlesinger, Arthur M., Jr. (Arthur Meier), 1917-2007; Schmidt, Benno C., 1942-; Warren, Robert Penn, 1905-1989; Welty, Eudora, 1909-2001; Winks, Robin W., 1930-; Woodward, C. Vann (Comer Vann), 1908-1999; Wyatt-Brown, Bertram, 1932-2012; American Historical Association; Johns Hopkins University; Louisiana State University (Baton Rouge, La.). Press; National Association for the Advancement of Colored People; Organization of American Historians; Oxford University Press; Southern Christian Leadership Conference; Southern Historical Association; Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (U.S.); University of Oxford; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. Department of History
- Correspondence, 1927-2000; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of both incoming and outgoing correspondence and is arranged alphabetically by the last name of the correspondent. Correspondence that concerns official business of a university, professional organization, or the like is filed under the name of that body. Letters to and from prominent individuals and organizations are filed in separate folders, as are those of correspondents with whom Woodward exchanged more than a few letters. All others are arranged in general folders at the beginning of each letter of the alphabet. Additional correspondence related to Woodward's writings and various subjects can be found in Series II and Series III.
  There is considerable correspondence between Woodward and his colleagues, students, and publishers. These letters in particular provide insight into the professional life of one of the twentieth century's best-known scholars. With his colleagues and friends, Woodward discussed a range of topics, including mutual academic interests, their current scholarly projects, and contemporary politics. Among his more notable correspondents were Cleanth Brooks, Virginia Durr, Ralph Ellison, John Hope Franklin, Richard Hofstadter, Dumas Malone, Daniel Patrick Moynihan, Walker Percy, David Potter, Arthur Schlesinger, Jr., and Robert Penn Warren. There is also very limited correspondence with such figures as W. E. B. Du Bois, Medgar Evers, Alger Hiss, Martin Luther King, Jr., Katharine DuPre Lumpkin, and Eudora Welty.
  Woodward counted among his students some of the most influential historians of the late twentieth century, and he remained in touch with them long after they left Johns Hopkins and Yale. Their correspondence evolved from that of mentor and student to that of colleagues and friends. Earlier correspondence deals chiefly with research plans and dissertation progress, while later correspondence concerns everything from new book projects to family life. Among Woodward's most prominent student correspondents were John Blassingame, Bertram Wyatt-Brown, Barbara Fields, Sheldon Hackney, James McPherson, William S. McFeely, and Willie Lee Rose. There is additional correspondence between Woodward and his graduate students in Series V.
  University presses such as the Louisiana State University Press and Oxford University Press are also well-represented in the series. Of particular note is Woodward's correspondence with Oxford University Press regarding the Oxford History of the United States series, for which he served as a general editor from the late 1950s until his death. This correspondence includes many letters to and from Richard Hofstadter, his co-editor. There are also numerous exchanges with authors and prospective authors for the series, all of whom were well-known historians. These include Stanley Elkins, William Freehling, Merrill Jensen, David Kennedy, Eric McKitrick, and James McPherson.
  There is voluminous correspondence concerning both Johns Hopkins University and Yale University, where Woodward taught from 1947-1961 and 1961-1977, respectively. Folders for Johns Hopkins include letters to and from colleagues such as Charles Barker, George Boas, and Sidney Painter, and more personal correspondence can be found under each colleague's name. Folders for Yale University include correspondence with colleagues Alexander Bickel, John Blum, Peter Gay, and Howard Lamar, as well as Yale Presidents Kingman Brewster, Bartlett Giamatti, Benno C. Schmidt, Jr., and Richard Levin. As with Johns Hopkins, there is also personal correspondence filed under the last names of many of Woodward's Yale colleagues. (For additional materials on Yale, see the Series V.) In addition to general correspondence with Oxford University, there are many letters concerning Woodward's term as Harmsworth Professor in 1954-1955. These include both official correspondence dealing with his appointment at Oxford as well as personal correspondence during his year in residence there.
  Woodward served as president of three major professional history organizations: the Southern Historical Association (SHA) (1951-1952), the Organization of American Historians (OAH) (1968-1969), and the American Historical Association (AHA) (1969). There is a large amount of correspondence for each of these organizations, particularly the American Historical Association. Woodward presided over the AHA's contentious business meeting in 1969, when proposed constitutional amendments and an unresolved AHA presidential election incited vigorous debate over whether or not the AHA should be a strictly professional, politically-neutral organization. The debates centered in part on the question of whether the AHA should take a stand on United States involvement in Vietnam. Many of the letters for the AHA, OAH, and the SHA concern Woodward's participation as either a presenter or commentator at each organization's annual meeting. There is also considerable correspondence between Woodward and organizations such as the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, the American Philosophical Society, and the National Institute of Arts and Letters, and such scholarly journals and newspapers as the American Scholar, the Baltimore Sun, Harper's Magazine, the Journal of American History, the Journal of Southern History, the Nation, the New Republic, and the New York Times.
  Although Woodward was actively involved in the civil rights movement, there is relatively little correspondence with other activists or civil rights organizations. The most significant letters dealing with the civil rights movement are scattered throughout the series, either under files for such organizations as the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People, the Southern Christian Leadership Conference, and the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee, or under the last names of individuals in the South who wrote to report local civil rights news. With few exceptions, the correspondence with civil rights organizations is routine correspondence dealing with meetings or conferences that Woodward was invited to attend. Of the prominent civil rights activists listed earlier, only Virginia Durr exchanged more than a few letters with Woodward.
  There is relatively little correspondence of a personal nature in this series. Woodward maintained semi-regular correspondence with a small number of extended relatives and friends from Arkansas and Georgia. Among them were his college friend Glenn Rainey and Arkansas friend C. R. "Dick" Huie. A handful of letters to and from his wife Glenn are included in this collection, as are a few from his only son, Peter. There are also a few letters to and from his parents, Hugh and Bessie, and his Uncle Comer. There are several letters to and from his daughter-in-law, Susan Woodward, with whom he maintained a close relationship until his death. (Researchers should consult Series VI for additional personal materials.)
  - A (general), 1938-1996, undated (Box 1, Folder 1 - 6)
  - Aaron, Daniel, 1950-1986, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Alexander, Thomas, 1956-1982, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Allen, Harry C., 1955-1956, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Ambrose, Stephen E., 1964 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - American Academy of Arts and Letters, 1954-1999 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1956-1988, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - American Association of University Professors, 1938-1975, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - American Civil Liberties Union, 1957-1978 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - American Council of Learned Societies, 1955-1977, undated (Box 2, Folder 15 - 16)
  - American Heritage, 1954-1997 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - American Historical Association, 1950-1999, undated (Box 3, Folder 18 - 25)
    General
    See also: Series III. Subjects, 1947-1997 Folder 1
    See also: Series I. Correspondence, 1926-2000, n.d. Folder 735
  - American Historical Review, 1938-1981 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - American Philosophical Society
    - General, 1950-1977, undated (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Membership nominations, 1962-1965, undated (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - American Political Science Association, 1956-1973 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - American Scholar, 1957-1997, undated (Box 4, Folder 30 - 31)
  - American Studies Association, 1954-1968 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Ames, Blanche Ames (Mrs. Oakes Ames), 1956-1965 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Ames, Jessie Daniel, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Amherst College, 1954-1972 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Amistad Research Center, 1971-1976 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Anderson, Charles R., 1955-1993, undated (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Anglo American Corporation of South Africa, 1963-1965 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Anti-Defamation League of B'nai B'rith, 1956-1992 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Aptheker, Herbert, 1954-1986 (Box 5, Folder 40)
    General note
    See also: Series V. Yale University, 1944-1994 Folder 1 - 4
  - Arno Press, 1968-1974 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Aspen Institute for Humanistic Studies, 1976-1977 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Association for the Study of Negro Life and History, 1948-1975 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Atheneum Publishers, 1961-1972 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Atlanta University, 1950-1968 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Atlantic Monthly, 1953-1990 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Auburn University, 1970-1971 (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Ayers, Edward L., 1995 (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - B (general), 1938-1998, undated (Box 6, Folder 49 - 56)
  - Bailyn, Bernard, 1960-1976, undated (Box 7, Folder 57)
    See also: Series I. Correspondence, 1926-2000, n.d. Folder 288
  - Ball, Douglas B., 1963-1975 (Box 7, Folder 58)
  - Baltimore Sun, 1951-1973 (Box 7, Folder 59)
  - Barker, Charles A., 1948-1982, undated (Box 7, Folder 60 - 61)
  - Barnard, Harry, 1950-1972 (Box 7, Folder 62)
  - Basic Books, Inc., Publishers, 1966-1980 (Box 7, Folder 63)
  - Beale, Georgia, 1975-1995, undated (Box 7, Folder 64)
  - Beale, Howard, 1937-1958, undated (Box 7, Folder 65 - 69)
    See also: Series II. Writings, 1935-1998 Folder 71
  - Beard, Charles, and Beard, Mary, 1953-1954, undated (Box 7, Folder 70)
  - Behrens, Anne King, 1938-1997 (Box 7, Folder 71)
  - Beloff, Max, 1954-1961, undated (Box 7, Folder 72)
  - Benson, Lee, 1954-1973 (Box 8, Folder 73)
  - Berger, Raoul, 1976-1979 (Box 8, Folder 74)
  - Bergstraesser, Arnold, 1940-1941 (Box 8, Folder 75)
  - Bickel, Alexander and Joanne, 1963-1971, undated (Box 8, Folder 76)
  - Billington, Ray, 1960-1968 (Box 8, Folder 77)
  - Black, Hugo L., 1940; 1958 (Box 8, Folder 78)
  - Blassingame, John, 1968-1999 (Box 8, Folder 79)
  - Bleser, Carol, 1976-1997 (Box 8, Folder 80)
  - Blum, John Morton, 1960-1998, undated (Box 8, Folder 81)
  - Boas, George, and Boas, Simone, 1952-1956, undated (Box 8, Folder 82)
  - Bobbs Merrill Co., Inc., 1954-1973 (Box 8, Folder 83)
  - Bode, Frederick A., 1965-1976 (Box 8, Folder 84)
    See also: Series V. Yale University, 1944-1994 Folder 14
  - Bonadio, Felice A., 1959-1973 (Box 8, Folder 85)
  - Boorstin, Daniel, 1953-1962 (Box 8, Folder 86)
  - Boston University, 1962-1980 (Box 8, Folder 87)
  - Bowdoin College, 1957-1958 (Box 8, Folder 88)
  - Bowen, William M., 1951-1953 (Box 8, Folder 89)
  - Boyd, Julian P., 1953-1969 (Box 8, Folder 90)
  - Brandeis University, 1956-1983 (Box 8, Folder 91)
  - Breaden, Dale, 1957-1958 (Box 9, Folder 92)
  - Brock, William R., 1958-1974, undated (Box 9, Folder 93)
  - Brooks, Cleanth, 1968-1987, undated (Box 9, Folder 94)
  - Bruchey, Stuart, 1956-1985, undated (Box 9, Folder 95)
  - Burlingame, Michael and Sara Lee, 1970-1997 (Box 9, Folder 96)
  - Burner, David, 1969, 1993-1996 (Box 9, Folder 97)
  - Burns, Ken, and Burns, Ric, 1987 (Box 9, Folder 98)
  - Burton, Vernon, 1992-1999 (Box 9, Folder 99)
  - Bush, George, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 100)
  - C (general), 1939-1998, undated (Box 10, Folder 101 - 108)
  - C (general), 1938-1997, undated (Box 11, Folder 109 - 110)
  - Calhoun, Daniel, 1955-1962 (Box 11, Folder 111)
  - Campbell, Charles, 1952-1967, 1998 (Box 11, Folder 112)
  - Capers, Gerald, 1950-1982 (Box 11, Folder 113)
  - Carleton, William G., 1938-1982, undated (Box 11, Folder 114 - 117)
  - Carlton, David, 1976-1981 (Box 12, Folder 118)
    See also: Series V. Yale University, 1944-1994 Folder 15
  - Carson, Suzanne, 1948-1956, undated (Box 12, Folder 119)
  - Carter, Dan, 1969-1995 (Box 12, Folder 120)
  - Carter, Jimmy, 1976, 1981 (Box 12, Folder 121)
  - Chappell, David, 1991-1999 (Box 12, Folder 122)
  - City University of New York [includes Bernard Baruch College, Brooklyn College, City College, the Graduate Center, and Queen's College], 1955-1982 (Box 12, Folder 123)